<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-09T21:42:41+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Welcome to My Blog</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Why FOSS is not able to hold the fizz</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/towards-libre-freedom/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why FOSS is not able to hold the fizz" /><published>2019-01-09T01:18:41+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-09T01:18:41+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/why-foss-is-losing-fizz</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/towards-libre-freedom/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-foss-is-not-able-to-hold-the-fizz&quot;&gt;Why FOSS is not able to hold the fizz?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no greater addiction than that of the freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freedom, as they say is always cheaper no matter at what cost it comes. Freedom, in my opinion is by far the most abused word and most of the socio-political groups today attack the very social fabric under the seeming innocuous name of &lt;strong&gt;freedom&lt;/strong&gt;. As much as they might like, the Governments of the world, in their public rhetoric at least, could not be completely oblivious to the evergrowing demands FOSS activists for the freedom [of software].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are diligent enough to embrace the history we can see that the main reason behind most of the revolutions is the freedom , irrespective of what the freedom is attributed to. For any revolution to be successful, it is important for the revolutionaries to create enablers and propagate the value that they are fighting for. They need to ensure that the people are convinced that the battle is worth fighting. And as long as this doesn’t happen the revolution will not gather much steam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a recent conversation with some of the well known FOSS activists from my region which included an entrepreneur and an academician the focus slowly shifted to the fact that the FOSS activity is not gaining the expected momentum inspite of socres of volunteers are working towards the cause. The organisations associated with FOSS are undertaking numerous activities ranging from weekly sessions , creating new GLUGs (GNU / Linux Users Group) in colleages to bi-annual sessions that cover from installation of any Linux flavour to ML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the obervations which all agreed to democratically was that, the focus of the volunteers in the recent past has shifted more towards teaching the technology which is in alignment with FOSS and how to technically contribute to any free software or open source software. A perhaps apocryphal notion has it that learning these technologies make one a geek or helps the student community to land at a better job or one among a plethora of reasons. Not getting into a mode of framing this into good,bad,right,wrong etc. I would like to reiterate that we are digressing from the core issues for which houndres of thousands of FOSS activists are fighting for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I belive that the central dogma of FOSS is all about the freedom , i.e “Free software is software that gives you the user the freedom to share, study and modify it. We call this free software because the user is free” - FSF. I have to painstakingly mention that this very essence of freedom is not present in most of the students who demonstrate interest in being associated with FOSS organization in their local geographies ( at the very least where I am currently). I believe it is not too late for us to imbibe this value of freedom so that it can drive them towards appreciating free software for what it stands rather than the notion of being looked upon as a geek, causing an aridity in the revolution. {: .justify}&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Why FOSS is not able to hold the fizz?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Towards libre hardware</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/towards-libre-freedom/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Towards libre hardware " /><published>2019-01-08T01:18:41+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-08T01:18:41+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/towards-libre-hardware</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/towards-libre-freedom/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;towards-libre-hardware&quot;&gt;Towards libre hardware&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thought-process&quot;&gt;Thought Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;history of mankind&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;civilizations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;social fabric&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;role of collaboration and education in society&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how important is the freedom aspect of education&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how it lead to FOSS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technology embracing history&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open hardware&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ML on open hardware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since the civilisations have started flourishing, there has been a constant endeavour to make them self sustainable. Sustainability demands free and fair access to the resources. The unfair gate keeping processes on access to these resources create  strata in the social structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered what is the most successful entity in the world ? I am sure there are umpteen number of answers considering the varied perspective each one of us have. But if I were to distinguish objectively then, in my opinion &lt;strong&gt;collaboration&lt;/strong&gt; should be the one word answer. 
&lt;em&gt;Collaboration&lt;/em&gt;, is the thread which keeps the social fabric very strong. Having said that, I view society as a large group of individuals who are proportionately dependent on each other. Apart from &lt;em&gt;collaboration&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;education&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt;(of speech,expression etc.) are the most important threads which make up the social fabric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Education&lt;/em&gt; in particular, has been of great interest for me for a long time. One of the main purposes of education is to create an egalitarian society and to achieve this education has to be free (free as in freedom).  There has been a lot of emphasis on this aspect of education and lot of activists are spreading awareness on the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can say in all senses that  &lt;a href=&quot;https://stallman.org/&quot;&gt;RMS&lt;/a&gt; has extended the free / freedom aspect to softwares and has been an ardent activist for more than 3 decades now. And it wouldn’t be wrong if I mention, that &lt;em&gt;collaboration&lt;/em&gt; has been the key strength of the FSF. I should mention that diversity has been so important and vital to freedom software and that comes from collaboration. More often than not many different ideas influenced by different cultures and walks of life melt in a melting pot due to collaboration and that’s the beauty of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without collaboration on such a scale, none of the open source / free software would have been as successful as they are today. the evolution of Free and Open Source Software (FOSS) is nothing less than a technological and philosophical revolution. 
Technology has to embrace the history if it has to serve its purpose lest we never make any progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of late, of all the technologies available, Machine Learning (ML) in particular is gaining a lot of traction owing to its very diverse use cases ranging from something as simple as a spam filter to something as complex as trading and life sciences. A lot of progress has been made in the past decade or so. Most, if not all the frameworks are based on open source platforms and I believe FOSS should get its due credit apart from MOOC in the particular case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, much of these frameworks still need a &lt;em&gt;proprietary&lt;/em&gt; hardware. What if we had an open source hardware that supports these frameworks or ML Algorithms and we could build individual ASICs algorithm per se ? I think this marriage between these open source frameworks and the open hardware can beget some truly open platform for ML Algorithm / framework development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With ML and AI and pattern recognition piercing into the consumer centric domain such as FMCG , retail etc, the algorithm developed and running on the proprietary hardware could be dangerous as they could invade the consumers’ privacy as one does not have full control over the functionalities of the proprietary hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that now arises is that can we come up with an approach where we can use a open source FPGA boards and design algorithm specific ASIC?  Can the philosophy of freedom become a reality in its true sense? Is there a societal will and a political will to make it realise ?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Towards libre hardware</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deobfuscating Machine Learning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ml-for-all/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deobfuscating Machine Learning" /><published>2019-01-08T01:18:41+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-08T01:18:41+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/deobfuscating-machine-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ml-for-all/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;de-obfuscating-machine-learning&quot;&gt;De-obfuscating Machine Learning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One word is too often profaned 
For me to profane it.
One feeling too falsely disdain’d,
For thee to disdain it. 
	&amp;gt;    – &lt;cite&gt;P.B Shelly&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With technology comes more power and with more power comes responsibility. Every technology comes with it’s own subtle terms and conditions and the major one being using it with utmost responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, unfortunately the knowledge one has about a technology has become synonymous with the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;jargons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; one can remember and use. The more obfuscation you create, the more knowledgeable you are. It is only unfortunate that we have are institutionalised to such social conditionings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think jargons are by no means the measure of knowledge. The purpose of knowledge is not to prove the possession of it rather the implementation. I think it is only apt to quote Miles Kington here :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Knowledge is knowing that a tomato is a fruit, wisdom is not putting it in a fruit salad.
 –&lt;cite&gt; Miles Kington &lt;cite&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of education should be to create enablers and not subscribers who subscribe to convenience of using jargons. I see excessive use of jargons as an attempt to make the knowledge proprietary and monetize it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not attempting to frame the act of monetizing the knowledge as long as it is not intended to create knowledge parasites out of the learners.  I am starting a series of articles where I will be taking on the mission of de-obfuscating the Machine Learning jargons and give away a very simple explanation of those terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;eg:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linear Separability :
&lt;img src=&quot;https://rdcnewscdn.realtor.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/LA-traffic-jam.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Traffic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you draw a straight line anywhere on the above picture such that it separates the vehicles going in either directions ?
The answer is a simple Yes. Just draw a straight line on road divider  (in most cases where traffic rules are followed) . Hence we say that the vehicles going in either directions are linearly separable.
Mathematically , Let &lt;img src=&quot;http://bin.sensegates.com/s/9/e/1/9e18f94ce7b1bda0a4742a1fd4437581.png&quot; alt=&quot;X_{0}&quot; /&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://bin.sensegates.com/s/5/f/5/5f5bcbe5a5e9accc4ea20a6ef79d196d.png&quot; alt=&quot;X_{1}&quot; /&gt; be two sets of points in an n-dimensional space. Then &lt;img src=&quot;http://bin.sensegates.com/s/9/e/1/9e18f94ce7b1bda0a4742a1fd4437581.png&quot; alt=&quot;X_{0}&quot; /&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://bin.sensegates.com/s/5/f/5/5f5bcbe5a5e9accc4ea20a6ef79d196d.png&quot; alt=&quot;X_{1}&quot; /&gt; are linearly separable if there exists n+1 real numbers &lt;img src=&quot;http://bin.sensegates.com/s/c/0/e/c0e25b8de3fa94adf05d5c879e89ec30.png&quot; alt=&quot;w_{1}, w_{2},..,w_{n+1}&quot; /&gt;, such that every point &lt;img src=&quot;http://bin.sensegates.com/s/b/b/e/bbe1a02df9fc417afc789df67e8f1e4b.png&quot; alt=&quot;x \in X_{0}&quot; /&gt; satisfies &lt;img src=&quot;http://bin.sensegates.com/s/e/6/7/e6745dadeb87bae8b149b6a66bd6cb1e.png&quot; alt=&quot;\sum^{n}_{i=1} w_{i}x_{i}\ge w_{n+1}&quot; /&gt; and every point &lt;img src=&quot;http://bin.sensegates.com/s/2/1/4/2141fb86544d6e3da389719546b52b19.png&quot; alt=&quot;x \in X_{1}&quot; /&gt; satisfies &lt;img src=&quot;http://bin.sensegates.com/s/6/b/4/6b47466dcbac320a2247b44b4aa9c585.png&quot; alt=&quot;\sum^{n}_{i=1} w_{i}x_{i} &amp;lt; w_{n+1}&quot; /&gt;, where &lt;img src=&quot;http://bin.sensegates.com/s/6/4/b/64b94619c0031522d16b05a37bc06189.png&quot; alt=&quot;x_{i}&quot; /&gt; is the i:th component of &lt;img src=&quot;http://bin.sensegates.com/s/9/d/d/9dd4e461268c8034f5c8564e155c67a6.png&quot; alt=&quot;x&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-be-continued-&quot;&gt;To be Continued …&lt;/h3&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">De-obfuscating Machine Learning</summary></entry></feed>